Finding Aid for First Congregational Church, Ann Arbor, Mich., Records, 1847-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
First Congregational Church, Ann Arbor, Mich., Records 1847-2012
First Congregational Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
2 phonograph record albums
3 oversize volumes
19 linear feet
86755 Ba 2; BA outsize
The First Congregational Church of Ann Arbor, Michigan, was organized and established on March 23, 1847. Records include administrative files, subject files, published material, and visual and audio-material.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the church in multiple accessions: from church historian Calvin O. Davis (donor no. 1973 ) in 1947; from church pastor the Rev. Leonard A. Parr (donor no. 2792 ) in 1950; and from different representatives of the church (donor no. 5878 ) in 1978 and later accessions.
The record group is open to research.
This history was taken from the church's homepage, Feb. 2011.
Additional details can be found in A History of the First Congregational Church in Ann Arbor 1847-1976 (published by the church). This volume includes a reprint of the earlier history by Calvin Olin Davis covering the period of 1847 to 1947.
The First Congregational Church of Ann Arbor, Michigan, was organized and established on March 23, 1847. The church was formed when its first members split off from the local Presbyterian church, both on the issue of slavery and over certain doctrinal positions.
The early beginnings of The First Congregational Church of Ann Arbor can be traced to a log school built by John Allen on the northwest corner of Third Street (now Main Street) and Ann. Worshipping together at this location were Catholics, Baptists, Episcopalians, Methodists, Unitarians, and Presbyterians. In cold weather, services were held in private homes. First Presbyterians and then Methodists began taking seats apart and finally holding services at a different time from the others.
On February 9, 1847, forty-eight members of the Presbyterian Church who had roots in Congregationalism were dissatisfied with the Presbyterian form of government and disagreed with the Presbyterian minister who would not renounce Negro slavery. This group met to begin formal steps toward severance and to select a site for a new church. Two weeks later the lot selected was purchased for $600.
During the building of the new church, the new Congregational Society held services in the courthouse. The church actually consisted at the time of two organizations: "Church" for spiritual matters and "Society" for business affairs. It would be the year 1913 when the "Church" and "Society" merged. After a number of "supply ministers" (ministers who would take a temporary one-year assignment with the church) and several attempts to procure a permanent minister, the Reverend L. S. Hobart of Union City, Michigan was hired November 18, 1848.
The newly built Congregational Church building on the corner of Fifth and Washington Streets in Ann Arbor was dedicated on June 21, 1849. By 1851, the church had 113 members. Two years later the church adopted a resolution against slavery, excluding from membership and as ministers any slaveholder or advocate of or apologist for slavery.
As membership grew, a resolution was passed to build a new church building at the present location at the corner of State Street and William Street in Ann Arbor. The cornerstone was laid on June 23, 1872. On May 10, 1876, the present building was dedicated.
The Congregational-Disciples Student Guild was formed in November 1942 as the church grew. This vital organization continues today as the Guild House Ministry to University students.
The church continued to grow physically also. In 1953, the Douglas Memorial Chapel, Pilgrim Hall, the Mayflower Room, offices, and classrooms were added. A fifth renovation of the chancel area in 1985 saw the installation of the Wilhelm organ, the third in the Church's history.
The records of the First Congregational Church of Ann Arbor have been divided into the following series: History/Background Information; Administration; Financial Records; Church Organizations; Topical Files; Miscellaneous later records; Photographs; Publications; and Phonograph records. The records document church administration, membership activities, and the relationship of the church to its denomination and to other area churches. Included are records of communicants, baptisms and marriages (1873-1905); pew subscriptions and accounts (1878-1939) and other membership information; minutes and reports of the board of trustees and the church council; records of men's and women's church groups such as the King's Daughters, the Ladies Aid Society, the Women's Fellowship Society, and the Women's Foreign Missionary Society; records relating to the church's affiliation with the Ann Arbor-Washtenaw Council of Churches; and files pertaining to the proposed merger of the Evangelical and Reformed Church with the Congregational Church in the 1950s.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Church history.; Ann Arbor - Washtenaw Council of Churches.; Congregational churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Evangelical and Reformed Church.; International Order of the King's Daughters and Sons.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Women--Religious life--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Congregational churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; First Congregational Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Stained glass--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors
Douglas, Lloyd C. (Lloyd Cassel), 1877-1951.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- History/Background Information
  - Brief history of First Congregational Church; dramatic historical sketch entitled "Voices of the Past'' (Box 1)
  - Memorandum regarding the organization of the church 1933 (Box 1)
  - Anniversary celebrations (Box 1)
- Administration 1847-2007
  - Covenant 1847 (copy); and reports of the Covenant Committee to the Church Council (Box 1)
  - Constitution and by-laws, articles of association, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Annual reports 1885, 1936-2011 (some gaps), 16 folders (Box 1)
  - Reports and other documentation 1913-1932 (Box 1)
  - Local church yearbook reports 1957-1963 (Box 1)
  - Clerk's record book 1847-1916 (Volume 1)
  - Record of communicants, baptisms, and marriages 1873-1905 (Box 2)
    (microfilm copy available)
  - Membership roll 1847-1906 (Box 2)
  - Membership list 1916-1994 (scattered dates), 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Pew subscription and accounts
    - 1878-1879 (Box 2)
    - 1879-1880 (Box 2)
    - 1894-1908 (Volume 2)
    - 1909-1925 (Box 2)
    - 1926-1939 (Box 2)
  - Board of Trustees
    - Meeting minutes
      - 1915-1918 (Box 3)
        (minutes and other materials accumulated by trustee Shirley Wheeler Smith)
      - 1915-1926 (Box 3)
      - 1934-1938 (Box 3)
      - 1939-1958 (scattered dates), 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1944-1953, 1 volume (Box 3)
      - 1953-1961, 1 volume (Box 3)
      - January 1961-December 1962 (Box 3)
      - January 1963-1965 (Box 3)
      - February 1965-January 1967 (Box 3)
    - Meeting minutes / treasurer's reports
      - 1970-1973, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - 1974-1978, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 4)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 4)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - Annual reports and other materials of the chairman of the Board of Trustees 1915-1933, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Every Member Canvass 1935-1965 (Box 4)
  - Annual meetings 1943-1982 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Church Council
    - Meeting minutes
      - 1950-2008 (some gaps), 11 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Executive Committee of the Church Council
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Minutes (Box 4)
    - Joint Meeting minutes (Church Council and Trustees) (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Special Meetings 1966-1981 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Board of Deacons
    - Meeting minutes 1972-1983 (Box 5)
    - Retreats; questionnaires 1959-1965 (Box 5)
  - Board of Deaconesses
    - Meeting minutes
      - 1954-1962 (Box 5)
      - 1962-1966 (includes manual) (Box 5)
      - 1973-1974 (includes manual) (Box 5)
      - 1975-1983 (Box 5)
- Treasurer / Financial
  - Annual reports
    - 1912-1914 (Box 5)
    - 1927-1953 (scattered), 1 volume (Box 5)
    - 1935-1944 (Box 5)
    - 1945-1949 (Box 5)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 5)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960-1964 (Box 5)
  - Annual reports to Michigan Corporation and Securities Commission 1935-1977 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 5)
    - 1909-1913 (Box 5)
    - 1914 (Box 5)
    - 1915 (Box 5)
    - 1917-1929 (Box 5)
  - Loan and grant applications; mortgage discharge 1931-1932 (Box 5)
  - Reports; miscellaneous financial correspondence, lease agreements. 1931-1939 (Box 5)
  - Mortgage agreement and discharge 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - Mortgage agreement and discharge 1951 (Box 5)
  - Pilgrim Hall land (deed) 1949-1950 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous financial material 1918-1919 also scattered dates (Box 5)
  - Financial reports of various departments-various dates (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Church Organizations 1869-1983
  - Ariston League (Box 5)
  - Benevolences Committee meeting minutes; correspondence; memoranda; annual reports 1953-1978, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Boy Scout Troop 23 (Box 5)
  - Children's Mission Band undated (Box 5)
  - Children's Missionary Band 1884-1904 (Box 5)
  - Congregational Men's Club
    - Secretary's book 1917-1925 (Box 5)
    - Treasurer's book 1908-1926 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Congregational Society
    - Articles of Association 1869 (Box 5)
    - Records
      - 1869-1891 (Box 5)
      - 1891-1915 (Box 6)
    - Treasurer's reports 1892-1907 (Box 6)
  - Double M Club
    - By-laws; financial records 1955-1977 (Box 6)
    - Minutes; memoranda 1955-1962 (Box 6)
  - King's Daughters
    - Records 1899-1907, 1907-1910, 2 volumes (Box 6)
    - Records 1911-1915, 1915-1947, 2 volumes (Box 6)
  - Ladies' Aid Society
    - Records
      - 1847-1861 1869-1880, 2 volumes (Box 6)
      - 1880-1909, 1 volume (Box 6)
      - 1910-1916, 1 volume (Box 6)
    - Treasurer's records 1870-1916, 1 volume (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Library Committee (Box 6)
  - Long Range Planning and Advisory Committee Report 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - Music Committee
    - Meeting minutes
      - 1947-1952 (Box 6)
      - 1981-1983 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence; financial reports 1949-1962 (Box 6)
  - Religious Education Committee / Church School
    - Board minutes 1939-1984 (some gaps), 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Treasurer's reports 1952-1967 (Box 7)
    - Children's Day Bulletins 1924-1988 (Box 7)
    - Church School
      - General (Box 7)
      - Grades 1-5 Unit Packages (Box 7)
      - Parent Packet (Box 7)
      - Square's Game (Box 7)
      - Videotape February 1978 (Box 7)
    - Curriculum 1983-1984 (Box 7)
    - Directories, Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Order of the Robe1 (Box 7)
    - Pilgrim Practical Class Books 1967-1969 (Box 7)
    - Sunday School Attendance Records
      - 1957-1963 (Box 7)
      - 1963-1971 (Box 7)
    - Teacher's Manual 1969-1977 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Sigma Eta Chi (National Congregational Sorority)
    - Scrapbook 1920s-1934 (Volume 3)
    - History; by-laws; memoranda (Box 8)
    - Sigma Eta Chi, Miscellaneous 1941-1953 (Box 8)
  - Social Education and Action Committee
    - By-laws and miscellaneous 1950s-1970s (Box 8)
  - Student Work
    - Michigan Congregational Foundation, By-laws; minutes; correspondence, memoranda 1934-1953, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Women's Evening Group (Box 8)
  - Women's Fellowship Society
    - Meeting minutes
      - 1917-1925 (Box 8)
      - 1925-1942 (Box 8)
      - 1942-1954 (Box 8)
      - 1954-1956 (Box 8)
      - 1956-1958 (Box 8)
      - 1959-1969, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1970-1975 (Box 8)
    - Secretary's Reports (minutes, financial, etc.)
      - 1960-1967 (Box 9)
      - 1966-1973 (Box 9)
      - 1967-1970 (Box 9)
      - 1968-1970 (Box 9)
      - 1969-1973 (Box 9)
      - 1973-1975 (Box 9)
    - Activities (General)
      - 1950-1959 (Box 9)
      - 1960-1967 (Box 9)
      - 1966-1973 (Box 9)
    - Ann Bradford Circle
      - 1949-1959 (Box 9)
      - 1960-1965 (Box 9)
      - 1965-1972 (Box 9)
    - Annual Reports
      - 1956-1972 (Box 9)
      - 1972-1975 (Box 9)
    - Annual and auditing committee reports 1927-1950 (Box 9)
    - Annual reports of Women's Work to Michigan Congregational, Conference 1946-1960 (Box 9)
    - By-Laws (Box 9)
    - Committee and groups reports 1932-1949, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Correspondence
      - 1960-1967 (Box 9)
      - 1966-1973 (Box 9)
    - Directories / Yearbooks 1918-1971 (scattered) (Box 9)
    - Friendly Service booklet -- Women's Fellowship 1956-1969 (Box 9)
    - Housekeeping 1955-1968 (Box 9)
    - Lists (Box 10)
    - Survey-Women's Fellowship 1967 (Box 10)
    - Programs and Publicity (Box 10)
    - Treasurer's record book 1917-1942 (Box 10)
    - Treasurer Report
      - 1968-1975 (Box 10)
      - 1971-1975 (Box 10)
  - Women's Foreign Missionary Society minute books
    - 1899-1908 (Box 10)
    - 1909-1916 (Box 10)
  - Women's Home Missionary Society minute books
    - 1880-1894 (Box 10)
    - 1894-1908 (Box 10)
  - Women's Missionary Society treasurer's record book 1913-1928 (Box 10)
- Topical files
  - Ann Arbor-Washtenaw Council of Churches
    - Secretary's book 1965-1969 (Box 10)
    - Annual reports 1964-1971 (Box 10)
    - Directories of Ann Arbor churches (Box 10)
    - Minutes of board of directors, executive committee and annual meetings 1963-1971, 12 folders (Box 11)
    - Minutes of planning commission and other minutes 1979-1982 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
  - Building renovation, etc.
    - Building plans correspondence 1916-1929 (Box 11)
    - Chapel and Parish Hall addition specifications 1950 (Box 11)
    - Church building, Reports-miscellaneous (Box 11)
    - Decorating Committee; church alterations 1925 (Box 11)
    - Dedication, 1876 Rededication, 1942 100th anniversary, 1947 Parish House, 1952 Centennial Sanctuary, 1976, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Douglas Memorial Chapel windows
      - Correspondence 1941 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence and memoranda; includes window designer's worksheets 1932-1957, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - Facility Improvements (Box 11)
    - Feasibility study 1982 (Box 11)
    - Gifts 1952-1966 (Box 11)
    - Goddard Estate, Will copy; correspondence; property records; minutes (Box 11)
    - Goddard Committee 1943-1950, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Renovation and building program history 1941-1957, 2 volumes (Box 12)
  - Congregationalist and Evangelical and Reformed Churches, proposed merger 1950s-1960s
    - Proposed constitution, final draft of constitution for proposed merger (Box 12)
    - First committee study 1956 (Box 12)
    - Committee of Concern 1958 (Box 12)
    - Committee for Continuation of Congregationalist Christian Churches (Box 12)
    - Anti-merger material, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Pro-merger material (Box 12)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 12)
    - Jackson Association "incident'' Report 1956 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence (various dates) (Box 12)
    - Michigan Congregational Christian Conference, State Board, correspondence regarding implications of merger 1956, 1961 (Box 12)
  - Membership miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Michigan Congregational Christian Conference
    - Scrapbook pertaining to 105th annual meeting, held in Ann Arbor 1947 (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - National Association of Congregationalist Christian Churches (Box 12)
  - Pastors and related circa 1850-1965
    - L. S. Hobart 1848-1854 (Box 12)
    - Carl S. Patton 1900-1911 (Box 12)
    - F. M. Sheldon 1912-1914 (Box 12)
    - Lloyd C. Douglas 1915-1921 (Box 12)
    - Herbert Jump 1922-1927 (Box 13)
    - Allison Heaps 1928-1937 (Box 13)
    - Leonard A. Parr 1937-1957 (Box 13)
    - Fred E. Luchs 1958-1964 (Box 13)
    - Terry N. Smith, 1965- (Box 13)
  - Pastoral Search Committee
    - Minutes and evaluation sheets 1964-1965 (Box 13)
    - Vitae; correspondence 1964, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Personnel miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Projects (Box 13)
  - Slosson, Preston and Flora May (Box 13)
  - Southeastern Michigan Association of Congregationalist Christian Churches (Box 13)
  - Southeastern Michigan Congregationalist Churchwomen (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous later records 1980s-2007
  - Deacons/Deaconesses, Minutes, Correspondence (Box 13)
  - Directories: Membership, Staff, Committees (Box 13)
  - Fellowship Committee 1980-1984 (Box 13)
  - General Congregation
    - Correspondence (Box 13)
    - Minutes (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Nominating Committee (Box 13)
  - Printed (Box 13)
  - Rededication Fund, Progress Reports 1983 (Box 13)
  - Reports
    - Administrative Assistant 1986-1992 (Box 13)
    - Decade Task Force (Box 13)
    - Senior Minister (Box 13)
    - Strategic Planning (Long Range Planning & Advisory Committee) (Box 13)
  - Search Committee
    - Organist (Box 13)
    - Pastoral (Box 13)
  - Special Meeting, Minutes (Box 13)
  - Staff Retreat (Box 13)
  - Trustee
    - Budget 2006-2007 (Box 13)
    - Meeting Minutes 2004-2007 (Box 13)
  - Volunteering Information (Box 13)
  - Web Site Committee (Box 13)
  - Articles and Clippings (Box 19)
  - Christmas Advent (Box 19)
  - Church Information (Box 19)
  - Church Windows (Box 19)
  - Do You Know? (Box 19)
  - Easter, Lent: Holy Week (Box 19)
  - Fillers, 5 folders (Box 19)
  - Halloween (Box 19)
  - Mother's Day/Father's Day (Box 19)
  - Prayer's-Terry (Box 19)
  - Sermons, Terry Smith (Box 19)
  - Thanksgiving (Box 19)
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous, mainly photos of services, church building, both interior and exterior, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Photograph album re stained glass windows 1995 (Box 13)
- Publications 1899-2007
  - Church bulletins
    - 1908-1953, 11 folders; 1 small box (Box 14)
    - 1954-1978 (Box 15)
    - 1979-2005, 36 folders (Box 16)
    - 2006-2012, 16 folders (Box 17)
  - The Church News, 1947-1952 (scattered) (Box 17)
  - The Congregational Church Newsletter 1962 (Box 17)
  - The Congregational Messenger 1962-1969 (Box 17)
  - The Congregational Courier
    - 1972-1976, 5 folders (Box 17)
    - 1977-2004, 28 folders (Box 18)
    - 2005-2012, 8 folders (Box 19)
    - Index to "Do You Know" and "Know Your Church" columns 1972-1993 (Box 19)
  - Cookbook-Ladies' Aid Society 1899 (Box 19)
  - Instructional booklets (Box 19)
  - Publications and brochures (miscellaneous) (Box 19)
- Phonograph records
  - Lloyd C. Douglas Memorial Service February 17, 1951, 33 1/3 rpm record album (Box 1)
  - Delta Sigma Delta (national dental fraternity); Memorial Service at Los Angeles, California, by Dr. Leonard A. Parr, 33 1/3 rpm record album (Box 1)